ILGWU Legal Department Records 5780/107
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU Legal Department Records
1958-1980
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Siems, Frederick Rolle
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU). Education Dept
5780/107
5 cubic feet
5 linear ft.
Records (documents).
The collection contains files relating to the ILGWU's organizing and legal activities surrounding the Kellwood Company at several of its divisions throughout the southern United States through court documents, correspondence, clippings, organizing leaflets, and accounts and interviews of the strike.
5516275
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Z. Guttendorf, June 02, 2009
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, April 11, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was once one of the largest labor unions in the United States founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States. It was one of the first U.S. Unions to have a membership consisting of mostly females, and it played a key role in the labor history of the 1920s and 1930s. The union is generally referred to as the "ILGWU" or the "ILG". The ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, and political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. The ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union in 1995 to form the Union of Needle trades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE). UNITE merged with the Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees Union (HERE) in 2004 to create a new union known as UNITE HERE. The two unions that formed UNITE in 1995 represented only 250,000 workers between them, down from the ILGWU's peak membership of 450,000 in 1969.
Biographical / Historical
From very early on in its existence, the ILGWU had need for legal counsel, and this was handled in the union's main offices in cooperation with hired attorneys. As the union grew and especially after the passage of the Taft-Hartley Act in 1947, the union found cause to establish a Legal Department. The department provided general legal counsel to the union and its affiliates, worked to develop collective bargaining agreement terms, and represented the ILGWU in litigation and arbitration. After the formation of the Master Agreements Department in 1965, the responsibilities for developing CBA terms shifted to the new department.
Scope and Contents
The Legal Department records do not comprehensively document the ILGWU legal activities, instead focusing on specific cases or series of cases.
Two ILGWU cases are documented in the Legal Department records. The first case involved the Kellwood Corporation, and the second involved the Donnelly Garment Company. The records relating to the Kellwood case (5780/107, 5780/107 AV, 5780/107 P) include court documents, correspondence and memoranda, surveys of strikers, organizing leaflets and newsletters (from both the union and the company), Steve Honeyman's draft accounts of the strike, audio and transcripts of Honeyman's interviews with ILGWU members and staff, newspaper clippings, photographs, and other printed material. The Donnelly Garment Company's case against the ILGWU is documented primarily through transcripts of the case, legal briefs, and related court documents.
Records on series of cases are the most general and extensive of the Legal Department records. They include records on ILGWU cases in the U.S. courts (5780/081), records documenting cases before the National War Labor Board (5780/085), and records relating to a wide variety contract negotiations, arbitration proceedings, and courts cases (5780/063).
Researchers may find complementary material in the other parts of the ILGWU records, such as the papers of the international leadership, especially the papers of ILGWU presidents (Series IV); the records of local unions in instances where these affiliates were involved in litigation or arbitration (Series III); and the collective bargaining agreements (Series VI). Related collections at the Kheel Center include decisions of the Coat and Suit Industry's Impartial Chairman (6036/015) and decisions of the Dress Industry's Impartial Chairman (6036/017).
In the Legal Department records (5780/107), the collection contains files relating to the ILGWU's organizing and legal activities surrounding the Kellwood Company at several of its divisions throughout the southern United States (Little Rock, Arkansas; Lonoke, Arkansas; Brownsville, Kentucky; and Greenfield, Tennessee). In addition to court documents and correspondence and memoranda relating to the ILGWU's legal cases, these records contain documentation of the Kellwood strike, including surveys of strikers, organizing leaflets and newsletters (from both the union and the company), and newspaper clippings on the strike. Also includes Steve Honeyman's draft accounts of the strike, transcripts of his interviews with ILGWU members and staff who participated in the strike, as well as working materials from the negotiations between the ILGWU and Kellwood. Organizing leaflets from other shops in Arkansas, Missouri, Nebraska, and Texas are also included.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780: ILGWU records 5780/107 AV: ILGWU Legal Department Audio-Visual Materials 5780/107 P: ILGWU Legal Department Photographs 5780/081: ILGWU Legal Department Records 5780/063: ILGWU Legal Department Records 5780/162: ILGWU Legal Department Donnelly Garment Company v. ILGWU Records
Women's clothing industry -- United States; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- United States; Clothing workers -- United States; Industrial relations -- United States; Labor laws and legislation -- United States; Siems, Frederick Rolle, 1915-; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Legal Dept
5516275
- Siems, Frederick, 1967-1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Kellwood, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Finance Department of ILGWU (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Chambers, Eva, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Surek Casz, 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Kellwood Union Contract [folder 1 of 2], 1971 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Kellwood Union Contract [folder 2 of 2], 1971 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Kellwood: Grievance Case Arbitration [folder 1 of 2], 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Kellwood: Grievance Case Arbitration [folder 2 of 2], 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Kellwood: Grievance Hearing, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Kellwood: Grievances and Settlement [folder 1 of 2], 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Kellwood: Grievances and Settlement [folder 2 of 2], 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Kellwood: Idabel, Oklahoma, 1968-1973 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Kellwood Corporation, 1961-1973 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Kellwood: Compliance Proceedings [folder 1 of 3], 1971 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Kellwood: Compliance Proceedings [folder 2 of 3], 1971 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Kellwood: Compliance Proceedings [folder 3 of 3], 1971 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1968-1974 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Retirement and Medical Plans, 1966-1971 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Kellwood: Little Rock and Tennessee, 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Kellwood: Little Rock, 1967-1972 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Kellwood: Distribution and Discharges, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Chambers, Eva: Organizer, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Honeyman, Steve, 1966-1977 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Interviews, 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- ILGWU Elections, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Leaflets: Lonoke, Arkansas, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Leaflets: Byrd, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- State v. Chambers, Eva, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- State v. Ferguson, Lemmie, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Kellwood Company, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Survey of Kellwood Strikers, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Leaflets, 1971-1978 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Leaflets: Bogart, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Leaflets: Spotlight, 1966-1970 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Leaflets: Munsingwear, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Leaflets: Honey Togs, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Leaflets: Genesco, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Leaflets: Nelly Don, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Leaflets: Manila, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Employer Leaflets, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Little Rock, Arkansas, 1958-1960 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Flashbacks: Book One (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Genrty, Doris: Supervisor, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Plan B Project, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- ILGWU vs. Ottenheimer, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  Scope and Contents
  July 22, 1976
- Little Rock: Protest Parade [folder 1 of 2], 1967 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Little Rock: Protest Parade [folder 2 of 2], 1967 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Herman Marcus, Incorporated, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Little Rock: Union Leaflets [folder 1 of 2], 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Little Rock: Union Leaflets [folder 2 of 2], 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Ottenheimer Company Leaflets, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- ILGWU: Court Cases, Leaflets, Newspaper Clippings, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Ottenheimer Company Leaflets, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Little Rock: Leaflets, 1965-1971 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Union Leaflets and Newsletters, 1965-1967 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Striking and Decisions, 1966-1973 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Kellwood Strikers: Special Medical Relief, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Strikers Health and Insurance Survey (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Greenfield Manufacturing Company [folder 1 of 2], 1971 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Greenfield Manufacturing Company [folder 2 of 2], 1971 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Lonoke, 1966-1972 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Brownsville, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Alamo [folder 1 of 2], 1967-1969 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Alamo [folder 2 of 2], 1967-1969 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Negotiating Exhibits, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Insurance and Police, 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Martin et al. v. Rockefeller, et al., 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Geraldine Booth, v. Frederick Siems, 1968-1970 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- State v. Hubman, Lillian, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- State v. Baily, Paul (Scab), 1967 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- State v. Hobbs, Darnell, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- State v. Wilson, David, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- State v. Jackson, Jerry, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Negotiations [folder 1 of 2], 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Negotiations [folder 2 of 2], 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Kellwood Company, Ottenheimer Division and ILGWU, AFL-CIO, 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Kellwood: Respondent's Brief, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Interviews: Youngdahl and Martin, Eldora (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Miscellaneous, 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Kellwood: Miscellaneous, 1966-1976 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- ILGWU v. Kellwood: Little NLRB cases, 1959-1970 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  Little Rock, Arkansas
- ILGWU v. Ottenheimer: Negotiations, 1965-1967 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- ILGWU v. Ottenheimer [folder 1 of 2], 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- ILGWU v. Ottenheimer [folder 2 of 2], 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- ILGWU v. Ottenheimer: Trial [folder 1 of 3], 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- ILGWU v. Ottenheimer: Trial [folder 2 of 3], 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- ILGWU v. Ottenheimer: Trial [folder 3 of 3], 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- ILGWU v. Ottenheimer, 1966-1967 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Ottenheimer: Refusal to Bargain Charges, 1966-1968 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- ILGWU v. Ottenheimer: Strike and Negotiations [folder 1 of 3], 1966-1967 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- ILGWU v. Ottenheimer: Strike and Negotiations [folder 2 of 3], 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- ILGWU v. Ottenheimer: Strike and Negotiations [folder 3 of 3], 1966-1967 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Ottenheimer Strike Injunction [folder 1 of 2], 1966-1967 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Ottenheimer Strike Injunction [folder 2 of 2], 1966-1967 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Sears Roebuck and Company v. Lambert, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Daley, Eloise F. v. Ottenheimer, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Past Strike Documents, 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- ILGWU Court Briefs, 1965-1978 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Jackson, Jerry (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Lavey, Jack (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Clay, Glenn (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Siems, Frederick (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Lupo, Alice (Box 5, Folder 19)
- Martin, Art (Box 5, Folder 20)
- Glenn, Ida (Box 5, Folder 21)
- Youngdahl, James (Box 5, Folder 22)
- Perlstein, Jerry (Box 5, Folder 23)
- Webster, Lew (Box 5, Folder 24)
- Wilson, Jean (Box 5, Folder 25)
- Jefferson, Bobby, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 26)
- Burlison, Nellie (Box 5, Folder 27)
- Cato, B.C., 1976 (Box 5, Folder 28)
- Roberts, Florence (Box 5, Folder 29)
- Martin, Eldora, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 30)